My name is Gernot, and I'm
a senior program manager
here at Google, New York.
I work for a
department called GEO,
which is responsible
for Google Maps and
our maps products
on Google Search.
A senior program manager is
typically responsible
for a set of
projects and initiatives all
the way from the ideation stage,
all the way through to getting
them launched and landed.
Something that happens to any
project manager on
pretty much almost on
a daily basis is that
there's something
unforeseen that happens,
and projects go off track.
Retrospectives are a
really important tool
in the toolbox that every
project manager should have.
Often people say at the
end of a project, "Okay,
now it's time to
do a retrospective,"
and you're sort of carefully looking
at what are the things that
happened that went well
and that didn't go well,
and what are some of the
learnings that you can
apply to future projects.
But I really think
of this more as
a continuous exercise
along the way.
Like, you really should be
continuously checking in on
how is the project going.
One example of
where a retrospective
has helped us get
back on track is,
we were working on the project,
where we are launching
something on
Google Search. Halfway
along the way,
we realized there's
actually a better way to do
this that would realize
much bigger benefits
to our users.
As a result of that,
we really got the
whole project team
together, and we really sort of
talked through, what
have we done so far?
What is it that the current
state of the project is?
What are our options to
go forward to help us
address some of the shortcomings
that we have not identified?
And then collectively
replan the rest of
the project to make sure
we're sort of in a clear path
forward and we have a clear
understanding of how to get
to that new understanding
of adjusted success.
It's incredibly important to be
flexible and adjust
direction if needed.
Like, if you know that there's
a change that's needed
and you know that the project
is going in a bad direction,
continuing in that bad direction,
obviously, is the worst
thing you could do for
the project and for the company.
It's really important to,
as quickly as possible,
initiate that process
of analyzing,
what are the options in terms of
things that we can do
to course correct and
make sure the project is
off in a good direction
and embark on that new direction
as quickly as possible.
Obviously, while taking
enough time to make
sure it's a data-driven decision—all
the stakeholders and
sponsors are on board.
The most important things
to keep track of as
a project manager really depend
a little bit on the project
that you're involved in.
So really I think tightly
managing the scope,
tightly managing the resources,
tightly managing against the
timeline that you set out,
and really carefully
assessing how things are
going as you compare them to
the plan that you
laid out originally,
and then use it to make
course corrections
as needed based
on the things that you see.